Welcome to five reasons profit lies
hidden in inventory why profitable
brands still feel cash poor. We are
excited to have Carly Lesters from
Ledger Gurus and Madison Kichun is from
Finale and we're going to keep going.
Awesome, thanks Kelly. Yes, I'm Carly
with Ledger Gurus.
I'm going to introduce myself. I kind of
have a unique background. I have started
and run businesses myself. I spent a lot
of time in education teaching
accounting, business, entrepreneurship,
technology. And I really love helping
people understand how business works,
not just the numbers, but actually
business itself.
Over the last couple years, I've been
working with Ledger Gurus and been
specializing in inventory accounting and
operations.
And what I've found is that
the inventory issues aren't really
accounting problems, but they're really
operational problems that show up in the
financials. So, what we love to do is
help businesses connect those dots. So,
they can look at their day-to-day
operations
down into the numbers, so we can
actually get a good gross margin that
helps them make better business
decisions. So, I'm really excited to be
here with Madison today. We have worked
with lots on lots of projects together
and with lots of clients. We have a lot
to talk about and lots to share. So,
Madison.
Thank you, Carly. And yes, equally as
excited to be here with you as well. And
a little bit of background about me. So,
Madison Kichun over here, partner
manager at Finale. I started at Finale
about, yes, it's coming up on 6 years
ago now. Started in the customer
relationships area and moved into
partnerships. Um, something about
relationship building and working with
our partners to find the best solutions
for our clients is something that really
resonates with me. And like Carly said,
helping people is kind of the core of
what we do here. So,
working with Carly and our clients and
our projects have been really exciting
and rewarding and I'm excited to get
into the kind of nitty-gritty today and
share with you what we've learned.
So, I'm going to introduce Ledger Gurus
a little bit. Um, Ledger Gurus was
founded in 2014 with a goal of helping
people build good, accurate financials
so they could run their business.
And we specialize in e-commerce
accounting, um, around sales tax, um,
revenue recognition. We have lots of
advisories services. But, what we're
What we're going to talk about most
today is our expertise in inventory and
COGS. And how we help businesses
determine what they actually don't know
about inventory. So, we work through
them. We talk about their pain points
together. We work through their
processes, their operations, their tech
stack. We go from purchasing all the way
through fulfillment and make sure that's
flowing clean down into the financials.
Because at the end of the day, inventory
it doesn't it doesn't start in
accounting, it starts in operations.
And
if that foundation's off, so are the
numbers. So,
um,
we want to we want to bridge that gap
between accounting and operations and
make sure what's reflected on the
balance sheet as inventory is right and
that your COGS is being expensed
correctly, calculated correctly, um, and
recognized right so that you have
margins that actually mean something and
that you can trust. So, um,
we do also like to partner with software
and technology that our clients are
using so we can understand how it works.
We can support them and help them
better. Make sure we're getting those
good numbers. So, again, why we partner
with Finale, one of our favorite
softwares that we use, a lot of clients
use. And so, we like to make sure we can
support them in that.
Awesome. Um, now a little bit about the
Finale side. So, Finale started in 2010.
We are a cloud-based inventory
management solution. We provide
real-time tracking inven- inventory
tracking across multiple channels,
multiple locations for high-growth e-com
sellers. We have a seamless integration
with QuickBooks and it is a direct
integration keeping operations and
financials in check giving you kind of
one centralized solution to look at your
inventory, operations, accounting, all
of it.
So, I'm going to go over the agenda for
today. We're going to start with the
five top reasons why profit gets hidden
in inventory. I'm excited to go over
these reasons together. And then we're
going to give you a three-step fix that
can help you if if you find yourself not
understanding your profit and what's
going on with it. We're going to give
you a three-step fix. And then we're
going to discuss how inventory flows
through the financials so we understand
that piece and the tools you can use to
become more efficient either in your
operations or in the accounting. And
we'll have a good Q&A after that.
Awesome. So, I will be kicking it off
here. So, something we hear from
founders all the time is, you know,
we're profitable, but why does it still
feel tight? So, you know, sales are
growing, orders are coming in, the P&L
says business is profitable, but cash
might still feel tight, margins still
seem inconsistent, numbers don't always
line up with what's happening
operationally. And most of the time, the
issue isn't sales, it's inventory,
unfortunately.
As brands grow, inventory becomes more
complicated. You know, you add more
SKUs, more sales channels, more
warehouses, more suppliers. And then all
of the sudden inventory isn't just a a
list of products anymore, it's a whole
system that's connecting purchasing,
operations, and accounting.
So, the tricky part is that every
operational decision has a financial
impact whether you kind of realize it or
not. So, like receiving inventory
affects your asset value, shipping
inventory, you know, triggers COGS,
freight and duties change your product
margins. But, I feel like these
connections often happen, you know,
behind the scenes. So, today we're going
to walk through five common places where
profit gets hidden inside inventory and
how businesses can start uncovering it.
And we're going to start with the first
question. So, the first reason. And
before we go into that reason, I'd like
to see ask you all question and maybe
raise your hand in the chat.
How many of you have seen your margin
swing from month to month and you
couldn't fully explain why?
So, you look at your margin swinging all
over the place.
I think a lot of people feel this
sometimes and that is a really big red
flag. And a lot of time our mind will
will automatically go to the sales side
and we start thinking, oh, is it
discounts? Is it is it our ad spend? Is
it is it, um, something seasonal? Where
in reality that might be and probably is
something to do with inventory,
inventory timing, or changes in costs.
And and I know that, uh, Madis- Madison
can speak to that a lot better than me,
but what happens to inventory that
causes that margin to swing, Madison?
I mean,
a lot a lot of things, you know, maybe
it's, you know, same product, you know,
prices change, duties increase, tariffs
change, your manufacturer costs changes.
A lot of, um, you know, kind of
different things that, you know, if your
product costs costs aren't being kind of
updated consistently or inventory
adjustments are being recorded, your
margins, you know, start to drift. And I
feel like that's kind of usually that
first signal that your inventory data
and your financial data are, you know,
starting to disconnect. And, um,
and usually happens when, you know, when
you aren't kind of tracking that
inventory movement cleanly. So, like
maybe you're selling inventory before it
you're selling inventory before it's
actually sold, you know, creating
negative stock. Or like I said, maybe
freight costs or landed costs get added
later which change your product costs,
you know, after sales have already
happened. Or another common thing is,
you know, adjustments get entered
manually at the end of the month to
reconcile the numbers, but, you know,
from the financial side, margins
suddenly start to move. But, from the
operations side, the business might feel
like, you know, nothing's really
changed. But, that disconnect between
what's physically happening with
inventory and what's happening in the
financials is usually that signal that
something deeper kind of needs
attention.
Yeah, especially if it you it's the same
products, the same pricing, you have the
same supplier, nothing's changed, well
then probably should dive into your
inventory a little bit. Yeah.
And reason number two, when your landed
costs get overlooked. So, I do have
another question for the audience here.
Just this little show of hands. When you
think about your product costs, are you
including everything in it to that it
took to get your product to your
warehouse?
I think a lot of people
this can be such a big thing that people
miss or it can just be hard, so it's
hard to do. And when we think about
coming up with that product cost, it's
easy to say, well, I bought it from the
vendor for 10 bucks, so that's how much
it costs, right? But, we have to
consider everything that it took, the
cost that you spent, the expense that
you you put out to bring that product to
your warehouse and get it ready to sell.
That's why it's the cost of goods sold.
A lot of people forget all those extra
things from freight, duties, tariffs,
um, insurance, packaging. And when you
bring all that in, it changes the cost
of that product, which can affect so
many things. Most people do their
pricing off of the cost or our COGS is
based on that cost. And so, I love this.
It says 60% margins on paper, actually
48% reality [clears throat] because
there's that phantom profit because of
all those costs that weren't considered.
Let's uh reason number three.
So, question again for you.
How many of you are still using
inventory, or sorry, using spreadsheets
to track inventory?
Or even like, how many of you maybe just
do it in your head or on a whiteboard?
Um Pen and paper. Manually. Yeah, pen
and paper. Which is not Not that any of
this is bad, but how many of people are
are doing that, right?
Um
And a follow-up question,
is you fully trust it? Like, do you
trust your spreadsheets?
I want you to think. And I can't see the
show of hands. I don't even know how
many hands we have going up, but I have
a feeling there's quite a few few people
that [clears throat] still do that. And
it does work great. I love spreadsheets.
I love spreadsheets, a good old
spreadsheet. And it works great for
inventory. If you have 10 or 50 SKUs,
you got one location, costs don't change
very much. Um one person's in charge of
it and good at spreadsheets, but what
happens, um Madison, as as things grow
in inventory with our spreadsheets?
The spreadsheets typically typically
break. And it's not not a fail
overnight. It's kind of they just slowly
stop telling that, you know, the full
story there. I feel like, you know, they
Yeah, like you said, you know,
spreadsheets spreadsheets were great
when you have, you know, 20 products,
everything is pretty stable. But as you
add more products, you add more sales
channels, you add more locations, your
costs is changing variably kind of with,
you know, the environment we're in
today.
Those the causes your spreadsheets to
break, you know, one All it takes is
kind of one formula to break or someone
overriding a number to make something
reconcile. And then suddenly your your
numbers on your spreadsheet don't don't
look right anymore. They don't quite tie
out any
Yeah, and you don't even realize it
until you see a problem in the
financials, right? You're just going
along thinking it's
>> like that's the moment that you kind of
realize. Yeah, and you don't even
realize it until you see a problem in
the financials, right? You're just
going along thinking it's doing good cuz
it's just a slow thing. [clears throat]
Then all of a sudden,
oh, it's not working. Then you have to
fix
>> Right.
So, if you love your spreadsheets,
I don't know. I love my spreadsheets.
Yes. [laughter]
But there might be a better way. Might
be a better way.
Yep.
Let's see. Oh, number four. Go Madison.
>> No one owns the numbers. So, a little
show of hands here, or I guess maybe if
you could drop it in the chat, who owns
the inventory at your company? Is it
ops? Is it accounting? Is it a mix?
I will say that I feel like we usually
see a split. We usually see a split. So,
we usually see operations owning the
units and what's happening in the
warehouse. They're responsible for, you
know, receiving the inventory, picking,
transferring, keeping stock moving. And
then the accounting side owns the
dollars. So, like what shows up in the
financials, product costs, all that
great stuff. But then no one knows No
one owns the full picture. And the
challenge is that, you know, inventories
lives in both worlds, in the operations
and the financials. So, when there isn't
a clearly defined owner, things can, you
know, start slipping through the cracks.
You know, for example,
actually have a a kind of interesting
anecdote here. So, when, you know,
costs aren't getting updated and, you
know, supplier prices change, you know,
landed costs get added, you know, months
after the fact, someone makes a
connection or, you know, correction,
this creates, you know, problems
essentially. So, the company might think
their system is broken, but when you dig
deeper, it's actually the fact that no
one owns things like product costs or
inventory adjustments. We've seen
situations where product costs haven't
been updated in 8 months because
everybody assumed somebody else was
responsible for it.
So, you know, sometimes the issue, you
know, isn't the system, isn't the
software. It was the structure around
who owns the numbers. And, you know,
tools can support the process, but they
can't replace ownership. So, like
inventory accuracy really starts with
clear roles, responsibility, and
consistent updates.
Yeah, and understanding each other's
roles. I found as I've worked with
clients, some people, you know, I can
ask them their role and they can tell
me, but they can't tell me what the
other people are doing. So, you know,
the left hand's doing this, the right
hand's doing that. They didn't realize
maybe they're both doing the same thing
or they're counteracting each other or
nobody's doing one thing. So, making And
then there's some finger pointing,
right? And And then there can be some
contention.
>> [clears throat]
>> But if there if there's fully
full roles that everyone understands
across
and it's defined, it really does help
owning those numbers.
Are we to reason number five already?
Reason number five, when there's no
monthly reality check. So, how many
people out there
um are reviewing and validating your
inventory numbers every single month?
This we find is a really big gap with
people.
They'll wait until something feels off
and then they'll check it.
And
so, really making sure you have keep an
eye on your inventory, it's your biggest
asset, is really important. But we do
find this is a big big gap. People wait
till it doesn't look right, then they'll
get into it. It makes it harder to fix.
There's errors have been compounded over
months. Um and it can become a big
problem and and and costly to fix.
So,
check it. Check your inventory.
Yeah, and from an operational
perspective, that monthly check is
really important because, as you I'm
sure as a lot of you guys know here,
inventory is constantly changing and
constantly moving. And if those
movements aren't being reviewed
regularly, then those small
discrepancies can really slowly build
over time. And, you know, something
Sometimes it's something simple, maybe
freight costs increase for a few months
or supplier adjusted pricing. But if
those changes aren't reflected in the
product costs, in the margins, the
margins, you know, start drifting. And I
feel like that's why those monthly
reality checks are so important. It
gives the team a chance to step back and
ask, you know, do the numbers that we
see actually match what's happening in
the business?
You know, inventory hap- inventory
problems rarely happen overnight. They
usually kind of build quietly over time.
Monthly checks are really important.
Yeah, and they and they can be really
simple checks, like just looking at your
balance sheet and see if it ties out to
what you physically have or is close,
right? Or checking those margins and see
what they're doing. Seeing if there is
any anomalies. So, it it doesn't have to
be like a huge big thing, but just a
simple check helps a lot.
And we've been walking through these
five areas, and you might have
recognized a few of these in your own
business. And if you find yourself
saying, "Yeah, that sounds familiar." at
any point, the good news is you're
definitely not alone. These are the
exact challenges we see with growing
e-commerce brands all the time. And I
feel like the port- the important thing
to understand is that these issues
aren't, you know, caused by one big
mistake. They usually happen because the
business is, you know, growing faster
than their processes around inventory
are.
So,
you know, we talked about you know, for
example, you know, start you starting
with a spreadsheet that works great
early on, and then you add more SKUs,
more channels, more warehouses, and then
suddenly inventory becomes more complex.
But the good news is that these are
fixable. And it's not about having the
perfect data or rebuilding everything
overnight. The goal is really clarity.
Clarity around your numbers, your
processes, and the tools supporting the
business.
So, when we work with brands going
through this transition, we really focus
on these three key steps. First,
establishing your baseline.
Second, fixing the structural gaps in
your processes. And third, implementing
the right tools to support how your
business actually operates. And again
here, the goal isn't perfection, it's
clarity and having numbers you can
actually trust.
And first step here, establishing your
baseline. So, the first step in the I
feel like fixing anything any of this is
actually pretty simple. Before we start,
you know, changing tools or processes,
we need to understand what the current
state is today.
And that means establishing a a clear
baseline here. The one way to think
about it is almost like a a quick
diagnostic for your business.
Three areas that we look at are
tracking, costing, and accounting.
The first is tracking. How are you
actually tracking and valuing your
inventory today? For some businesses, it
might be through a spreadsheet. For
others, it might be looking at your
sales channel data. And some teams, you
know, have a full-blown IMS to help. And
then sometimes, honestly, it's just what
someone remembers in their head. So, the
key question here is whether you kind of
have a single source of truth for your
inventory.
And that second piece is costing. So,
are you capturing the true landed cost
of your products? That means including
things like freight, duties, shipping,
customs, anything like that. Because,
you know, the real cost isn't just what
you paid your supplier for the product,
it's everything it took to get that
product from that factory to the shelf
in your warehouse for sale.
And that third piece is accounting here.
So, do you understand how inventory is
actually flowing into your financials?
Inventory should be treated as an asset
an asset, not an expense, which means
that the cost of that inventory doesn't
hit your P&L when you buy it. It hits
the P&L when the product is sold and as
COGS.
So, a quick way to kind of check your
baseline is by asking, you know, a few
simple questions here. Do I know my
exact inventory count right now?
Do I know what that inventory is worth?
My product costs up to date?
Am I using accrual accounting? If any of
those questions are hard to answer,
that's usually a good signal that the
baseline needs some work. And at the end
of the day, you can't fix what you
haven't measured, and that's exactly
where this process
Yeah, I I love that first just
establishing your baseline and
understanding where you're at. Then it
leads straight into fixing the
structural gaps you might have. And this
is one of my favorite things to do with
clients is looking at those gaps cuz
sometimes we just don't know what we
don't know. So,
it takes maybe just talking it through
with someone or looking at that baseline
to see what might be missing later on.
As we talked about ownership, that's a
big one we start at. Who owns the
number? Who's the person? And not
everyone can do it, but who's the one
person that owns certain parts of the
processes, right? So, defining your
roles and who does what and
understanding what each person does is
really important. I think you'll find as
you do that, you better understand what
the whole company is doing in business
and how it works together. Then you'll
want to look at your processes.
We can't
create we can't put a process into a
tool or bring it into accounting if it
hasn't been created. And a lot of times
people aren't really sure what the
process is and they haven't documented
it. They haven't written it out, it's
just in their head. So, well, this is
what I do. Well, what happens if you're
not there and then someone does it
different. So, really understanding your
processes and getting them written out
in some good SOPs written out for
people. Processes from how do you
receive inventory, how you order it, how
do you transfer it to other places, how
are adjustments accounted for and put
in. Looking at trade shows and then
processes that lead into fulfillment in
sales. Your manufacturing, what do those
processes look like? And and honestly
just writing it out step-by-step,
creating some good SOPs so everyone
knows what's happening.
And then,
cycle counting is a big one. We have a
lot of We talked about checking
at least once a month.
And we have some businesses that need to
check more than once a month. They have
a lot and this is where cycle counting
can come in.
If anything at a minimum check and count
your inventory once a year. And if you
can do it monthly or if you have a ton
of inventory and it's it's too much, you
can cycle count. And so, we love cycle
counting. Make sure you have this
process well-defined and that you're
counting and checking inventory
regularly. And then ask yourself, here's
things you can ask. Can I name the
person who owns cost updates?
Who's the person in charge of cost
updates? Whether that's on a
spreadsheet, looking at vendor bills, or
if it is in a tool, someone's monitoring
those and making sure they're accurate.
Do I have a written SOP for receiving?
And and for every process
included. We'll say receiving, but is
there a standard SOP for how that is
happening?
When did the last Did we do a last cycle
count?
If you're like, I don't know, and we
don't have an established count or even
how we do the counting,
we need to That's a gap. That's a big
gap. Do we track every inventory
movement?
A lot of people think, well, yeah, we
track inventory coming in cuz we
purchase it and then inventory going out
for sales, but inventory leaves for a
whole lot of other reasons and those
need to be tracked. So, the tool doesn't
fix unclear ownership. People and
processes go first. So, before you
decide what tool you want to use or
maybe you're using a spreadsheet and you
want to update it
or just come up with a better process
for tracking your inventory,
this needs to be fixed first and
understanding who's owned it, the
processes, and how you're counting it
cuz that comes first, then the tool.
Oh, I love this slide so much. It just
It's
>> volumes, right? Garbage in, garbage out.
Meaning, Yes. if you don't have that
that structural and there's lots of gaps
or you don't even know where you're at
from the beginning,
you don't know what's going in, then
here we are as accountants or ledger
gurus on the end getting the numbers out
that aren't making sense and it's just
garbage. And we we find it's because
what's going in is garbage. And and
meaning what's going in, people maybe
don't understand what's going in. They
They don't understand they that they're
missing something that needed to go in.
So, garbage might be a strong word, but
we need to make sure the data going in
is actually accurate and that everything
is getting captured cuz we've said
before every
every inventory operation, every task
that happens operationally day-to-day
needs to be transformed,
translated into a financial number and
captured in in your books cuz really our
books, your balance sheet, your P&L, it
tells a story. I need to be able to look
at that and tell a story and the story's
going to be wrong if if what's coming
into my story is wrong. And it's
interesting cuz I met
this morning right before this, I was
meeting with a client, Donachie,
and Nelson told me he was going to be
here today and I hope he is cuz we've
been working on this. They actually use
Finale and we were trying to pull
numbers from there, but it was just We
were like, these cannot be right. And
so, they decided to have us come and
help them and work through what was
getting in. What was actually going into
the tool? Is what's going in right? And
so, if Nelson's here and I can't really
tell cuz I don't like um
Oh, he is not here.
Dang it. I wanted Nelson to maybe share
what that process has been like. So,
maybe I'll just share what I think he
might say.
It's been great. We've been meeting
weekly and going through all of their
operations. We talk about physically
what was happening and then looking how
they were doing it in the tool and we
found huge gaps. Things that were
happening weren't being put in the tool
correctly or they didn't even know it
needed to be put in the tool. There was
there was things happening that they
didn't understand. One person needed to
do it or the other There was no
ownership. There were no processes
written out. So, as we've written those
processes out, gave ownership, checked
the tool and make sure it's actually
reflecting what physically was
happening, we found so much that we've
been able to fix and now we can truly
look at the numbers in the tool and feel
good about those and accurate and we've
got good stuff coming out. I don't know
if you've had examples or experience
with that, Madison, where you've worked
with clients and understanding what goes
into Finale or in any type of tool. It
has to be good or it's not going to
produce anything good.
>> Yes, I That is definitely something we
see a lot, especially as businesses are
evaluating new systems. I feel like
sometimes the expectation is that the
new tool will automatically fix
everything. But if the underlying
processes, you know, around, you know,
receiving, you know, your operations and
things like that, the underlying
processes aren't clear, then those same
issues will just carry over into the new
system.
So, the tool is really is truly only as
good as what you put in it. And there
goes the saying, garbage in, garbage
out. And I feel like an accountant first
I first heard that saying from an
accountant, you know, because it's so
true for financials like you were
saying, Carly. If you're putting in, you
know, bad inventory numbers and bad
average costs and bad, you know, product
cost information, then the financials
that come out of it are going to be
inaccurate and that's not helpful when
you're trying to make, you know,
business decisions based on those
margins.
Um
but yeah, I mean, that's why I feel like
the first two steps we talked about are
so important, that baseline and
structural gaps because before
implementing any tool, you need to have
good processes that your technology can
support. We can't replace it, but it can
definitely support.
Yeah, and and you and you got to
understand those processes so when you
go in the tool, you understand what
you're putting in there. And someone
needs to manage it. It It's always like
you said, people pick a tool and hope
that it will just solve everything,
which it can Magic. long as you have to
still manage it, put the data in,
understand the processes, then it can be
magic. It can be. Yes. Sure.
>> [snorts]
>> And here we are on step three, so
getting the right tools. So, once
you've, you know, established your
baseline, you fixed your structural gaps
that we talked about earlier, that's
when technology and a tool can really
start to help.
And again, the right tool shouldn't be
expected to fix broken processes. It
should support and scale your processes
that already work.
And the first thing to look for is
accurate tracking. Your inventory system
should be able to track stock across all
your sales
all your sales channels, all your
locations in real time. Every inventory
movement from receiving to transfer to
adjustment to sale should be recorded
automatically. Where you're not
constantly trying to manually reconcile
or catch up at the end of the month,
which I feel like is very very
commonplace to be.
And that next piece is accounting. So,
your inventory system ideally should
connect directly to your accounting
system so your financials reflect what's
actually happening operationally. For
example, automatically calculating and
posting COGS when inventory is shipped
and syncing that data directly to
QuickBooks
eliminates that kind of manual process
of getting that data into QuickBooks by
a a human essentially and allows
inventory to be treated properly, you
know, as an asset rather than an
expense.
And that third piece is operations. Your
system should really reflect how your
business runs. That means, you know,
supporting your purchasing flow, your
warehouse workflows, the sales channels
you operate on today.
And just as importantly, grow with the
business as you add more products, more
channels, additional locations.
When you're evaluating tools, I feel
like, you know, there's some good
questions to ask. And those are Do I
understand my sales channel and
fulfillment flow? Do you understand how
your orders are being placed, how
they're flowing into your shipping
system, how they're getting picked and
packed?
Who on the team
will own this?
A big thing, like Carly said, I feel
like ownership of processes is a pretty
big deal. So, who on the team is
actually going to take ownership of
entering this data in the tool, like we
just talked about? If you're putting bad
data in the tool, you're going to get
bad data out of the tools. So, having an
ownership, having someone who is
responsible for making sure accurate
data is getting into your tools is super
super helpful.
And then, are my operations clean enough
for a tool today.
Another great question. If like I said,
you know, a tool doesn't fix broken
processes. It can help support your
processes that are working. So,
that kind of one of you know, those
first two steps, making sure your
baseline and fixing those structural
gaps and processes to make sure your
operations are clean enough to move to a
tool.
And then the last one here, am I ready
to move beyond spreadsheets? I would
like to think that most most people
would probably say yes, they're ready to
get off those spreadsheets, ready to get
out of those errors and looking at all
those lines, but um
but yeah, in the end, the right tool,
like I said, doesn't really fix your
operations. It makes the ones that work
visible and scalable, helping your
business grow.
Yeah, and and I love that tools
tools can be a spreadsheet, but you the
spreadsheet won't even fix
if there's a structural gap or you don't
know your baseline.
So, let's see how inventory becomes a
financial transaction. This is so I'm so
passionate about this and I know we've
said it, I'm going to say it again,
every physical action in your business
maps to a financial entry.
And
one thing I love about Finale and how
it's set up
is that it breaks it up into those main
operational activities around inventory,
purchasing, inventory, and selling. And
all of those operational activities flow
down into the counting module. And so as
we think about this and we think about
purchasing,
it's important to understand that when
you receive inventory into your system,
the inventory value is going to go up,
right? When you have those supplier and
invoices, you got to track, do we want
to pay it? Have we received it all? Um
have we not received it all? Do we need
to make some adjustments there? And it's
those POs in the purchasing that will
actually calculate that landed cost and
it's there where you put in all those
extra expenses we talked about to bring
the inventory to your warehouse. It's
placed on those POs. So, it's a really
important piece. And then in the middle
you've got your inventory and this is
where things go for stock changes and um
takes on your inventory. If inventory
goes out, most people think of inventory
leaving for just sales, but it goes out
for different reasons and that needs to
be captured in the system. And
operationally, people do that really
well, but then they forget to capture it
financially. So, all of that happens and
then the cycle um counts and making
numbers actually what you have.
And then on the selling side,
this is this is a big one cuz this is
where your COGS is. How am I fulfilling
my orders? Like Madison said, we've got
to talk about the fulfilling, the pick,
packing, and shipping. Can we make that
more efficient? How are they leaving? Do
I understand all the sales orders coming
in? Understanding that at that's the
time when you fulfill that COGS is
calculated and that's what's going to
flow into your financials. We need to
think about returns. Anytime you have a
return, is it getting back put back into
inventory? If so, that's going to change
the value and that needs to go into your
financials. The nice thing about a tool,
it helps manage that. I've seen people
try to do, we go back to the purchasing
side, they try to manage all their
purchase orders in a spreadsheet or
calculate a landed cost. It can get
really hard, especially if you start
purchasing a lot or your your costs get
really volatile and changing a lot. If
you've got a couple SKUs and your costs
never change, you probably could do it,
but the nice thing about a tool is it
keeps that updated cost for you all the
time and gives you some really good
numbers. And then that cost flows into
the selling side for COGS, calculates a
really good COGS. And why is COGS
important?
>> [clears throat]
>> It's their biggest expense. It's what
hits and gives you that gross profit
margin. So, we really want a good clean
COGS number when we think of accounting.
And all that comes down in the tool. So,
if your operations is good and ran right
and you're using the tool correctly,
it comes into accounting, makes
everything so pretty for us. And
remembering that every action becomes a
transaction financially.
And moving on to how Finale solves this.
So, on the previous slide we talked
about how every operational action in
your business eventually becomes a
financial transaction.
Purchasing affects inventory value,
inventory movements affect stock levels,
shipping,
you know, shipping sales triggers COGS
and that's, you know, exactly where
Finale comes in.
Everything starts with purchasing. In
Finale, you can create your create,
manage, and um execute your purchase
orders. You can receive inventory
against those purchase orders in
multiple shipments if needed.
And with those purchase orders, capture
that landed cost.
And so with our within the purchase
orders in Finale, like Carli said,
you're able to add adjustments, you
know, whether it's for duties and
freight and shipping and taxes. If it's
all of those things, we would add all of
those adjustments there. That way Finale
is calculating your true landed cost.
And as those products are received,
Finale automatically updates the unit
cost of your inventory. So, at any given
moment, you're able to click into a
product in Finale, see that cost, and
that is your true accurate average cost
today.
And then once inventory is in the
warehouse, Finale helps manage
everything happening operationally. So,
you get real-time visibility into stock
on hand across multiple locations,
support for cycle counting, transfers
between warehouse, inventory
adjustments. Finale keeps a stock
history log as well. So, as inventory
moves and changes, you can always audit
those operations and even make those a
part of your kind of monthly reviews
that we discussed a few slides back.
And then when products are sold, Finale
syncs with your sales channels within 5
minutes. So, we're pulling in orders
from your sales channels every 5 minutes
and then we're also pushing our stock
level back to those sales channels every
5 minutes to prevent overselling. That
way, you know, when you sell a product
on eBay, it doesn't get, you know, sold
on Amazon or on Etsy or on another
platform. Finale keeps all of your
channels in sync and everything aligned
and preventing that overselling.
We also help with that pick and pack
ship workflow as well in the warehouse.
And we do also have barcode scanning
application that helps improve picking
accuracy, warehouse efficiency, reducing
fulfillment mistakes. So, I'm not sure
sure um people in here have definitely
dealt with it, but maybe you're having,
you know,
a high number of mispicks or high number
of reships or things like that and
that's something where the barcode
scanning tool can really help
eliminate [clears throat] a lot of those
errors and um make that process a lot
more efficient.
And then as those operational actions
happen, Finale automatically records the
financial impact. So, when inventory
ships for a sale, COGS is recognized at
the right time and synced directly into
QuickBooks. Inventory is tracked as an
asset on the balance sheet rather than
being treated as an expense. And because
the product costs in Finale includes
your true landed costs, your margins
start reflecting the real cost of your
products that you're actually selling.
So, instead of guessing what the numbers
are,
and guessing what the numbers are and
make seeing if they're accurate, you're
able to look at your financials and
actually trust what the margins are
telling you.
So, instead of operations and accounting
living in separate worlds, in Finale,
everything kind of flows together in one
system. And that's what allows your your
inventory valuation, your margins, your
financial reports to reflect exactly
what's happening in the business.
And Finale doesn't, you know, we don't
replace your processes, we run on it.
And the cleaner your processes are, the
more the system can support and scale
with your business.
Yeah, and I want to make two comments on
here, Madison. That we maybe missed
maybe and maybe you talked about this,
but one thing I love as I've helped
clients, a lot of times clients will
come to me and a big pain point is just
reordering, when knowing when to
reorder.
And I love that about Finale or tools in
general, they can help you know when
when it's time to reorder. And that's
hard to do manually. Another thing I
love about tools and as an accountant,
if I look at the balance sheet and I
look at the inventory and I have this,
you know, this huge number,
I need to back that up. I need to have
an inventory valuation I can pull to
show, you know, this is my inventory by
SKU, by cost, by quantity and and I I
can like prove that number almost. I can
explain that story being told on a
balance sheet and it's right there in
Finale. It's easy to back up and it just
really adds to your financials. It makes
you feel confident in what you're
showing in your financials. Um and you
can go to Finale to pull all sorts of
reports to back those numbers up. If
you're using categories, if you're using
uh it just it adds so much and can open
up
and really tell the story of what's
happening with inventory that you can't
get on a spreadsheet or you can't get
from your head. So, I love that. I love
using a tool.
>> [laughter]
>> And so as we go to the next slide, it
says, how can LedgerGurus help you?
And and we can read through this slide,
but really um
we can help a lot of people who just
don't even know where to start or what
they need and help them get in a tool,
um decide if they're even ready for a
tool and what the right tool is for
them. We like to help them get clean, so
make sure the inventory on the balance
sheet is is a good number and is clean,
help you switch if if you're using cash
base accounting right now, switch to an
accrual base, help you fix any errors in
your COGS, your historical COGS that you
might have. Um we can [clears throat]
help you get really confident in making
sure you have a true landed cost that is
set up right, you feel good about it,
that it's flowing through the financials
correctly, that your product costs are
updated, whether you're doing that
manually or using a tool, and that we
can look at your monthly margins with
you, help you figure out and watch that.
We can help you get compliant in
different areas, sales tax and and nexus
with your filing and remittance.
Um our we're e-commerce specialists, so
we can help in all those areas. We can
help you get clarity on your P&L, make
sure you trust those numbers, that your
financials are built and are reliable to
make those good decisions. So we handle
the numbers while you handle your
operations and your business.
And one thing that we're offering now is
a free inventory reality check cuz again
sometimes people just don't know what
they don't know. They're not sure where
their baseline is even though we
presented some questions for you to help
start asking. We do have this inventory
reality check and there's a link in the
chat that you can use and it really it
goes through it's going to ask you some
questions to help you determine your
current state or that baseline and then
it's going to give you a result that
tells you where you're at risk, maybe
help you find where those structural
gaps are. Then it'll provide you with an
action plan and help you know where to
start and then give you some
personalized recommendations at the end
and give you just a good idea of where
you at with your inventory, where your
gaps are, what you may need to do, just
a little guidance there. It's a really
good tool that I recommend everyone just
using. It's free and you can just use it
and get some good information, do a
quick reality check of where you're at
with your inventory.
Yeah, if if anybody wants to dive deeper
in how this works in practice, we're
always happy to continue the
conversations. We have We have two QR
codes here. The first one here is to the
Ledger Gurus inventory consulting
services and the second is to schedule a
demo with Finale.
But yeah, we'd love to continue these
conversations. So please please you know
scan these QR codes and reach out and
we'd be happy to Yeah, talk about you
know these practices in real life and
how they
relate to your businesses.
I think we'd love to open it up to some
Q&A now. So if anybody has any
questions, please feel free to drop them
in the chat
and we'd be happy to answer.
Okay.
I think we've got a few here.
I'll read off the first one here and
this one is from a
attendee here. I feel like I spend a lot
of time on my financial inventory
process. Where can I be saving time?
Mhm.
Loaded question.
Yeah, so loaded question.
I feel like I spend a lot of time on my
financial inventory processes. Well,
Mhm.
I and I know Madison you feel this too.
We do. We spend a lot on the financial
and the accounting side not realizing
we're trying to figure it out from the
numbers,
but those numbers aren't right because
what's happening operationally
is wrong and so it's flowing into the So
maybe maybe maybe a suggestion here
would be
instead of looking at your financial
inventory processes, stop for a minute
and go review your inventory operations.
How's that going?
And then and then move back in. What do
you think, Madison? Like Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. I mean it kind of goes back to
those kind of the three-step fix we
talked about, you know, establishing
your baseline, kind of seeing where you
are in your current state today. What
are your operational processes? Is there
any, you know, opportunities to enhance
them or make them more efficient and are
those same, you know, inefficient
operational processes driving these, you
know, driving all this time you're
spending on your financial process, too.
But no, Carly, I think you're exactly
right. Kind of
making sure your operational processes
are clean and perfect and then I feel
like that's when it kind of flows
downstream and you start saving time on
your financial process.
Yeah, because you might Maybe you're
spending a ton of time trying to come up
with a good landed cost, but you don't
have all the right information. A tool
could help there, right? Cuz it could
calculate that. But maybe you're
spending a ton of time trying to track
quantities and trying to reconcile
quantities between your 3PLs and your
warehouse. I'm not and and try to come
up with the value, but you don't realize
that what there's no one in charge of
where the where the quantities are in
the 3PL or no one's actually in charge
of this There's so much that this is a
loaded question to me. So I'm like,
well, where are you spending your time?
Um and maybe we can add that in the chat
whoever asked that like
what what time are you spending Is it on
coming up with product costs? Is it just
trying to come up with a value? Are you
trying to You've got huge adjustments
all the time. Where are you spending
your time
specifically?
Maybe we could help more.
Let's see we've got another question. It
says COGS, margins, and more.
There is so many KPIs, which is the most
important one to focus on for my
business growth?
Mhm.
I man, I keep going back to the
operations, Madison. Like
you want to get to COGS and margins, but
maybe
start with that baseline and really
define your business and where you're at
and those gaps.
Um
Yeah. I feel like we're just saying the
same thing, but I feel really strong
about that cuz a lot of clients I meet
[clears throat] with
it really they do want to grow,
but they don't They want to grow,
so then we'll talk about well, tell me
about your purchasing process
and they don't have one. They're like,
well, I don't know. When I need it, I
purchase it. I'm like, okay, well,
where are you purchasing it? Where are
you tracking your POs? Who receives it?
Are you checking that what you've
received is what you actually ordered?
Who pays it? Do you just pay it or do
you make sure what you paid for you
actually received? If the cost changes
on the PO after you received it, are you
changing it and making sure your product
So like talking through it, then there's
a lot of of things that need to happen
before you can go to We want to go
straight to COGS and straight to margins
cuz that's where we
that's where our P&L is. We know it's
it's kind of like our scorecard, right?
Like how much we're making and it's our
profit and that's what we want to know,
but we skip all the other pieces that
get us to a good number.
Yeah, no, I totally totally agree with
that. And you know, it's it's sometimes
it might be even hard to rely on the
COGS you have or the margins you have
because maybe you're not tracking your
product fairly right now. So I feel like
it definitely like you said, I feel like
it always goes back to operations and
making sure that your your processes are
intact, the ownership is there, the
structural gaps are resolved and then,
you know, then your COGS and your
margins are more reliable numbers to
look at for business growth.
Yeah, and then if you do want to grow
and scale, get those get those tools in
place that can help you do that so you
can scale when you're ready.
Automate Yes, automate the inventory
syncing, automate the COGS posting,
automate, you know, landed cost
tracking. I think yeah, those are really
really big things to Yeah,
the business growth for sure. Yeah.
Yeah.
Let's see do we have another question?
When shipping costs are in
an order and shipping costs are in an
order. I'm assuming they mean sales
order, but maybe purchase order, but
we'll say sales order. How would you
divide those shipping costs
onto into the items? So maybe they are
talking purchase order. If they have
different costs, say an item is $89
and another is five, would you divide
each of the shipping fees into the cost
of each item by how many items or would
you your shipping cost go into more
expensive? All this is such a good
question. I mean it's done manually, but
you Do you want to explain how you do it
in Finale cuz Finale has several options
of allocating
>> Yes. They they call it allocating those
landed costs into the product cost and
I'll let you tell them how the different
ways and why you
Finale's great because they help help
you determine It's it's not the same for
every business, right, Madison? It it it
would be depending on the business.
And so I'll let you explain the
different kinds.
Yeah, I know you're exactly right,
Carly. So Finale does have multiple
allocation methods when it comes to
adding your shipping costs and your
adjustments to your purchase orders.
So we can we can adjust we can allocate
equally. We can allocate by quantity. We
can allocate by volume and we can
allocate by subtotal.
So if your if your, you know, your more
expensive products are carrying more of
the shipping costs, we can allocate by
subtotal which will land that shipping
cost higher on the more expensive item.
If you're you're maybe doing, you know,
um
and I'm no freight expert, but maybe
like freight container shipping and you
know, the bigger your product is, the
more of that shipping cost it holds, we
would want to allocate by volume. That
way the larger product is holding more
of that shipping cost weight.
And then we also have, you know, equal
distribution. Maybe, you know, you're
selling widgets all the same size,
shape, weight and they all get the same,
you know, same shipping cost allocated,
but we can do it equally as well. And
then quantity, too. So if your, you
know, your freight forwarder, whoever it
is, your freight provider, they are
charging you more for the, you know, the
more quantity that you have, we can
allocate based on quantity so that your
the product on the order with the
highest quantity gets the highest, you
know, shipping cost and then it flows
down to the rest of them.
But yeah, I'd love your your input on
that, Carly, and kind of what you see.
Yeah, and this is such a [laughter] this
is such an enlightening question because
it's important to think cuz I worked
with a client who did a big
shipping container like you said and
they had bikes on there, but the
shipping container also had just
[clears throat] some helmets, right?
Well, but so they just they weren't
thinking in the tool, right? They just
whoever was running the tool, they just
did it by quantity or something. So it
was a huge They were landing a tariff, I
think it was. So it was a big amount and
it changed the cost of the helmet.
>> [laughter]
>> So all of the sudden the cost of the
helmet went from like $2 to like $300
because that shipping should have gone
more to the bikes cuz that carried the
heavier load of it. So, just
understanding and it could be different
from
a shipping to a different one. You don't
have to do it all the same just because
it's how it works with this PO or this
vendor, it might be different with
another one depending on what you're
ordering. I mean, we've got clients
ordering stuff from
hundreds of vendors, right? Yes. So,
it's hard to pinpoint it into one and
this is again why you've got to make
sure those processes are written out
and everyone understands how are we
landing these costs for these items with
this vendor?
How are we managing it with this one?
Who's doing it? Cuz like I said, the
client I was working with, they didn't
know. They were They just were like,
"Oh, yeah, we just put it on the line on
the PO." They didn't realize they needed
to allocate it differently. It wasn't
written out anywhere. There were no
standard processes for that person to
follow and there was no ownership on who
actually put the costs in there. And
then on top of that, as the accountant,
I didn't realize they were landing
those. So, I was taking the tariff and I
was expensing it straight to the P&L cuz
they didn't tell me they were landing
it. So, now what happens, Madison? If I
already put it on the P&L and they put
it in the They landed to the product
cost, where am I going to see that
expense again?
Through COGS, right? Cuz now it's part
of the product cost. So, then
I'm now a double count of COGS pretty
much. It's going to So, your P&L, your
margins are off. Um So, but it was just
because
that person didn't know who how to put
it in. There was no standard operating
[clears throat] process written out.
Right. They didn't They didn't inform
the accounting piece cuz you got ops and
accounting a lot of times it's broken
up.
>> Yeah.
Didn't understand that they were landing
that, so we were expensing it. So, there
was no like communication lines. It's
just
Yeah.
Structural gaps, you guys. Structural
gaps. And And it's so fun cuz sometimes
people don't know what they don't know,
Madison. Literally. You know, they
didn't know what they didn't know. Yes.
>> Sometimes it just takes
time to think through it and, you know,
only cuz I have ran a business and
taught entrepreneurship,
we don't want to think about that stuff,
right? We want to We want to create cool
products and we want to sell them and
see how much we're going to make. Like,
who wants to worry about all of that?
You know, you really don't want
But all of a sudden your margin you
really you really have to. Or heck,
don't. Find someone in the business and
make them Give them that ownership.
Exactly. No, someone's got to take that
ownership and understands what it's
doing. Write out those SOPs. And if you
don't want to write them out, join us.
We'll help you. We'll talk through it.
We'll write your SOPs. We'll help you
find those holes and those gaps.
Cuz everyone has them.
Totally. 100%. Right? And no one is
alone in this. This These are I feel
like very universal issues
across I feel like a lot of e-commerce
brands. Yeah. Yeah.
And as more and more people are selling
on more and more channels,
right? And then you're buying from I It
just can get so complicated.
Yes. It really can. And then
>> Totally. I've also seen, I don't know if
you've seen this as as you start with
with a client that that doesn't not in
Finale or not in a tool. Maybe they're
using They're in three or four different
places. So, just trying to bring all the
data into one is exhausting. Maybe
that's what the first question was. How
do I save time? Maybe she's looking at a
spreadsheet for this and then she's in
um She's in a different
>> Amazon looking at her sales and
QuickBooks looking at the financials.
Yeah. So, we're spending hours just
pulling data
to try to connect the dots.
So, it's so relieving to have everything
in one system.
All your purchasing's there. Your sales
are coming in. So, we can just go to one
place and have that as the source of
truth when it comes to inventory.
Oh,
it's such a good feeling for sure.
Ooh, we got another question.
How does the data update in the system?
How does data update in the system?
I'm assuming we're referring
to Finale as the system, but um as far
as Finale goes, we are pulling in data
from your sales channels every 5
minutes. We are also syncing with
QuickBooks every 5 minutes. So, that is
about as close to real time as you can
get. So, you can imagine your sales
order comes in, it's shipped, Finale
records COGS, we send that COGS entry to
QuickBooks within 5 minutes. So, there
kind of eliminates that gap with that
manual reconciliation and kind of match
up your operations to the accounting
when you have a tool that is kind of
doing that already automatically for you
in the background as you do your your
day-to-day operations in the system. So,
as you receive purchase orders, your
inventory asset gets increased. You
don't have to go into QuickBooks and
increase your, you know, do a journal
entry, manually increase your inventory
asset. Those kind of manual aspects are
taken out of it when you have a tool
that is updating, you know, like I said,
every 5 minutes. I mean, it's pretty
pretty real time as I think you can get
nowadays.
And And on that purchasing side, so on
the sales side, it is pulling it from
the channel, so you don't really have to
do anything. But the sales orders are
coming in and doing things. But on the
purchasing side, you do have to enter
the purchase orders, right? Right.
>> receive them. You have to land your
costs. So, like as long as you have to
do that manual stuff, but the system is
right when you put in that landed cost,
this is This is the wonderful thing
about Finale, too. Although it might It
bugs some accountants, but maybe cuz I'm
a business-minded, I love it. You go in
and land a cost, you know what Finale
does? It automatically updates COGS that
maybe already happened. Fixes it. It's
like magic. Recalculates it all.
Recalculates the value of your
inventory. Syncs it all over to the
books. It's fabulous because how many A
lot of times people can't land a cost
for months, right? Right.
It is all It's pretty automatic. You go
in, you put it in there, hit it, it
recalculates the product cost,
recalculates COGS, sends it over. Bing,
bang, boom. I mean, you need to
understand what's happening. So,
a word to the wise,
don't try to map Finale or any tool or
connect it to a
system like QuickBooks unless you fully
understand what's going to happen cuz it
can It can be I I want to say it's
magic, but it can also be a disaster if
you
map it to the wrong place or don't
understand what's going to happen.
I'm sure people have horror stories, but
if you
if you do it correctly, it is like magic
and it does It happens automatic for the
most part. Totally. Especially, too, if
you work with the Ledger Gurus team to
help with that QuickBooks mapping and
that implementation, you are literally
set up for success. You, you know, set
up for success from the get-go with
them. So,
Totally.
I love it. We do really work good
together. They Finale makes sure the
operations comes in that they understand
to use the tool,
help it get connected and that the
financials look good.
Love it.
And the Ledger Gurus helps our clients
understand what's going on in their
financials, what they should map to
QuickBooks, what they should be syncing,
should they be landing their costs this
way, you know, are their current product
costs accurate based on, you know, what
they've entered before. I No, I Like you
said, definitely a dream team here and I
feel like with
Ledger Gurus on the accounting, Finale
on the operations, we are able to work
together and give them the accurate
numbers,
you know, accurate margins, a
centralized system, just
accuracy, efficiency all around. Yeah.
And just I love that you said efficiency
because it might be a lot of work at the
beginning, but you want to make sure
it's done right. But in the end, it's
going to save you time across operations
to accounting and it's going to align it
all and you can truly
look at your financials and see the big
picture. It tells the story and you can
make those good decisions that you need
to.
Yeah, and feel confident with it, too.
And we just want to help everyone, don't
we, Madison? We do. We do.
Main core is helping people, right?
Helping people in all aspects. And
understand. Yeah. Cuz we've seen a lot.
We've seen a lot.
And we love to learn. Do we know it all?
No.
There's many times I'm like, "Gosh,
I don't know." But we always can figure
it out together with clients and help it
work for them. So,
I knew this was going to be fun,
Madison. I did.
>> Everything with us is fun. Yes. I will
have to give Nelson a hard time for not
being here. But other than that, this
was fun.
Totally. Ladies, thank you so much.
Oops, I seem to be a ghost. I'm not on
there. Oh, well. I I Thank you so much.
This has been absolutely delightful and
I'm so glad that we were able to to have
you guys and your expertise and
everything. Thank you.
Thank you for having us. Yep. Bye,
everyone.
>> It was a pleasure. Have a great day,
everybody.
Take care.